Guide to the Thomas Wilfred Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Thomas Wilfred papers
1914-1993
1914-1968
MS 1375
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
24.75
The papers consist of correspondence, drawings, photographs, printed material, clippings, and miscellanea documenting the professional career of Thomas Wilfred, inventor of the clavilux and a prominent artist and developer of lumia, an artform which utilizes light as the medium of expression. Additional materials detail Wilfred's musical career as a lute player. The development of lumia within the field of kinetic art and the prominent role of Thomas Wilfred in this development, as an inventor, artist, performer, and teacher are documented. Correspondence with individuals, fellow artists, universities and organizations, and museums detail Wilfred's attempts to develop, promote and market the clavilux. Correspondents include: Eugene Epstein, Alfred N. Goldsmith, the Museum of Modern Art, W. Christian Sidenius, the Whitney Museum of Art, and several universities. Material detailing clavilux construction attempts and experimental work Wilfred performed, including extensive numbers of drawings, photographs and sketches of clavilux models, patents on the clavilux, contracts for performances, research data for design plans, compositions for "visual symphonies," and clippings and printed material on performances and recitals are included. Other materials include research data, clippings, and writings on the artform of lumia, and additional information for compositions written by Wilfred and articles published by Wilfred and others.
Wilfred, Thomas, 1889-1968
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Thomas Wilfred, 1983; W. Christian Sidenius, 1994-1995; Raymond Epstein, 1996; and Georgia M. Newton, 2009 (Accession 2010-M-026).
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, drawings, photographs, printed material, clippings and miscellanea documenting the professional career of Thomas Wilfred, inventor of the clavilux and a prominent artist and developer of lumia, an artform which utilizes light as the medium of expression, 1914-1968. Additional materials detail Wilfred's musical career as a lute player, 1914-1918.
The development of lumia within the field of kinetic art and the prominent role of Thomas Wilfred in this development, as an inventor, artist, performer, and teacher are documented. Correspondence with individuals, fellow artists, universities and organizations, and museums details Wilfred's attempts to develop, promote, and market the calivilux. Correspondents include: Eugene Epstein, Alfred N. Goldsmith, the Musuem of Modern Art, W. Christian Sidenius, the Whitney Musuem of Art, and several universities.
Material detailing the construction and experimental work Wilfred performed, including extensive numbers of drawings, photographs, and sketches of clavilux models, patents on the clavilux, contracts for performances, research data for design plans, compositions for "visual symphonies," and clippings and printed material on performances and recitals are arranged in the papers. Other materials include research data, clippings, and writings on the artform of lumia, and additional information for compositions written by Wilfred and articles published by Wilfred and others.
Biographical / Historical
Thomas Wilfred was born on June 18, 1889, in Naestved, Denmark. He studied music in Europe, achieving international status as a performer on the lute. He moved to the United States in 1916, and began to develop and perform on the clavilux and promote lumia as an art form. Wilfred died on August 15, 1968 in Nyack, New York. Wilfred toured the United States performing clavilux recitals, and appeared with such artists as Leopold Stokowski. He constantly designed new clavilux models, built and headed the Art Institute of Light in New York, adapted the clavilux for scenic projections in theatre productions, and composed over fifty compositions for the clavilux.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series and four additions: I. Correspondence, 1923-1968. II. Clavilux, Lumia, and Miscellanea, 1914-1968.
Other Finding Aids
For an index of books that are included in this collection, please consult the Bibliographical Index.
Art -- Study and teaching; Art, Modern -- 20th Century; Art; Composition (Art); Kinetic art; Light in art; Artists; Lutenists; Benton, William, 1900-1973; Epstein, Eugene; Goldsmith, Alfred N. (Alfred Norton), 1888-1974; Sidenius, W. Christian; Stein, Jules; Stokowski, Leopold, 1882-1977; Stulman, Julius; Vaill, George D.; Wilfred, Thomas, 1889-1968; Clairol, inc; Seattle Historical Society; University of Georgia; University of Nebraska--Lincoln; University of Oregon; University of Washington
- Correspondence, 1923-1968; Series I; 2 linear feet (4 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains Wilfred's professional correspondence as inventor of the clavilux, the light projection machine used to create works of "lumia," a kinetic artform which utilizes light as a medium. Wilfred built clavilux machines of various sizes and capabilities, ranging from large models for amphitheatre performances to smaller versions for use in homes. This correspondence includes items about theatres, universities, and locales where clavilux performances and exhibits were staged, including Clairol, Inc. of New York, the Musuem of Modern Art, the Metropolitan Musuem of Art, and the Whitney Museum of American Art, and the state universities of Georgia, Nebraska, Oregon, and Washington. Correspondence with Alfred N. Goldsmith concerns the mutual efforts of the two men to market the clavilux as a commercial venture. Similarly, letters exchanged with Eugene Epstein detail the interests of a typical art collector in the availability of the clavilux and lumia compositions for personal use. W. Christian Sidenius wrote Wilfred frequently from 1960-1968 and the two men discussed their work on lumia in detail.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically by individual and/or organization.
  - A (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - B (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bedford, Duchess, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Benton, William, 1953-1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Brooklyn College, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - C (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cameron, Norman, 1939-1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Carroll, Richard and Wright, G. Scott, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cassen, Jackie, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Clairol, Inc., 1959-1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cleveland Museum, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Collier's, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - D (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - E (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Eindhoven Museum, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Epstein, Eugene, 1962-1967 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
  - Epstein, Raymond, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - F (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Fassler, Victor, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Fresno State College, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - G (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Germer, Fenn, 1923-1926 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Goldsmith, Alfred N., 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
  - H (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Healy, John, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - I (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - J (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Jaeger, Karl, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Joffe, Marcus E., 1930 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - K (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Kleigl Brothers, 1956-1963 (Box 2, Folder 33-34)
  - L (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Laposky, Ben, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Lewis, Nolan, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Lighting Research Laboratory, 1923-1924 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - M (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Mc (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1954-1965 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Miller, James Hull, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1949-1967 (Box 3, Folder 43-44)
  - N (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - O (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - P (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Paramount Theatre, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    General note
    See also: Box 6 folder 99.
  - Philadelphia College of Art, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Pleper, Emmy, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Potter, Ralph, 1947-1949 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Q (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - R (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Richmond, Frederick W., 1954-1956 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - S (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - San Francisco Museum of Art, 1942-1964 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Seattle, Washington
    - Department of Parks, Undated (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Seattle Historical Society, 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 58-59)
  - Shook, G. A., 1928 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Sidenius, W. Christian, 1960-1968 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Singletary, Charles E., 1961-1964 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Stein, Jules, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Stockholm, Sweden: Modern Museum, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Stulman, Julius, 1955-1961 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - T (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - University of Georgia, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - University of Nebraska, 1952-1962 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - University of Oregon, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - University of Washington (Box 4, Folder 70-71)
  - V (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Vail, George, 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - W (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Y-Z (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 77)
- Clavilux, Lumia, and Miscellenea, 1914-1968; Series II; 22 linear feet (22 boxes, 2 folios)
  This series contains the research data, drawings, designs, patents, contracts, photographs, writings, clippings, and miscellanea relating to Wilfred's construction of clavilux models and performance of lumia compositions. The series is arranged in three sections: CLAVILUX, LUMIA, and MISCELLANEA.
  CLAVILUX files contain extensive clippings files on specific performances, models, and the Art Institute of Light (folders 86-101). Numerous drawings and sketches of clavilux models and components are also organized in this section, and include several large design plans found in boxes 22 and 23. Specific clavilux installations and performances at Carnegie Hall in New York City, and the Hotel Sherman in Chicago are also documented. Photographs (box 10 and folio 27) illustrate several clavilux models and picture Thomas Wilfred installing machines and performing various works.
  LUMIA files contain detailed instructions and plans for performing many of the compositions or "Opus" works which Wilfred authored. Major compoments of the clavilux, central to the performance of a lumia composition, are also documented, including the direct beam projector (folder 197), and the multiplate scenic projector (folder 210). The projected scenery application of lumia, that is, the use of the artform as the scenery in the production of a play, details another aspect of Wilfred's work (folders 214-216; 240).
  MISCELLANEA files contain material on Wilfred's musical career as a lute player in Europe, obituary notices, and photographs.
  This series is arranged in three sections: CLAVILUX, LUMIA, and MISCELLANEA. Material in each section is arranged alphabetically by topic and/or type.
  - Clavilux
    - "Americana,", 1928 (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - Art Institute of Light, 1938-1966 (Box 5, Folder 79-83)
      General
      See also: box 6, folder 96
      - Clippings, Undated (Box 6, Folder 96)
    - Bibliography, Circa 1925 (Box 5, Folder 84)
    - Carnegie Hall, New York, Undated (Box 5, Folder 85)
    - Clippings
      See also: box 13
      See also: box 24
      See also: box 25
      - General, 1924-1937 (Box 5, Folder 86-92)
      - General, 1928-1959 (Box 6, Folder 93-95)
      - Beginning to Model E, Undated (Box 6, Folder 97)
      - Model E, Undated (Box 6, Folder 98)
      - Paramount Theatre, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 99)
        See also: Box 3 folder 48.
      - Miscellaneous, Circa 1934-1942 (Box 6, Folder 100-101)
    - Composition
      - General, 1954-1959 (Box 6, Folder 102)
      - Opus 155: "Orientale,", 1962 (Box 6, Folder 103-104)
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 7, Folder 105)
    - Construction drawings: Models
      - B, C, D, E, and 10RK20, Undated (Box 7, Folder 106-108)
      - G, Undated (Box 7, Folder 109-110)
      - H, Undated (Box 7, Folder 111-112)
    - Contracts
      - Performances, 1918-1940 (Box 7, Folder 113-114)
      - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 7, Folder 115)
    - Drawings, Undated (Box 7, Folder 116-117)
      See also: box 8, folder 118
      See also: b ox 14, folder 198
      See also: boxes 22-23, folders 242-248
    - Drawings, Undated (Box 22, Folder 242-244c)
      See also: box 7, folders 116-117
      See also: box 14, folder 198
    - Drawings, Undated (Box 23, Folder 245-248)
    - Drawings, Undated (Box 8, Folder 118)
    - "Futurists,", Undated (Box 8, Folder 119)
    - Hotel Sherman: Chicago, Illinois, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 120-122)
    - Letters of appreciation, 1924-1946 (Box 8, Folder 123-127)
    - Notations, Undated (Box 21, Folder 239)
      See also: box 21, folder 239
    - Patents
      - Cases: 1-7; miscellaneous, Undated (Box 9, Folder 128-135)
      - Color and music, Undated (Box 9, Folder 136-138)
      - Foreign, 1924-1926 (Box 9, Folder 139)
      - Hallock-Greenwalt, Mary, Undated (Box 9, Folder 140)
      - United States, 1922-1934 (Box 9, Folder 141)
    - Photographs
      - Carnegie Tech., Undated (Box 10, Folder 142)
      - Compositions, Undated (Box 10, Folder 143)
      - Home model, Undated (Box 10, Folder 144)
      - Keyboard, Undated (Box 10, Folder 145)
      - Projectors, Undated (Box 10, Folder 146)
      - Sidenius, W. Christian, Undated (Box 27, Folder 249)
        See also: box 27
      - Studio: Huntington, New York, Undated (Box 27, Folder 250)
      - University of Georgia, Undated (Box 10, Folder 147)
      - University of Washington, Undated (Box 10, Folder 148)
      - "The Vikings", Circa 1928-1930 (Box 27, Folder 251)
      - Wilfred, Thomas, Undated (Box 10, Folder 149-152)
        - Oversize (Box 27, Folder 252)
        - Research data, Undated (Box 12, Folder 168-170)
    - Posters for Wilfred performances, Undated (Folder 28)
      Large poster is in poor condition.
    - Poster for Wilfred performance, Undated (Box 22, Folder 244d)
    - Projected scenery: University of Washington, Undated (Box 21, Folder 240)
      See also: box 21, folder 240
    - Projected settings
      - Chicago World's Fair, 1933 (Box 10, Folder 153)
      - Seattle, Washington, Undated (Box 10, Folder 154-155)
        See also: box 21, folder 241
      - Seattle, Washington, Undated (Box 21, Folder 241)
    - Publicity, Undated (Box 10, Folder 156-158)
    - Recitals
      - Audience members, Undated (Box 11, Folder 159)
      - Requests, Undated (Box 11, Folder 160)
    - Research data, Undated (Box 11, Folder 161-167)
    - Scrapbooks, 1918-1928 (Box 24)
      See also: boxes 24-25
    - Scrapbooks, 1926-1942 (Box 25)
    - Sears, Roebuck, and Co., 1934 (Box 12, Folder 171)
    - Sketches, Undated (Box 12, Folder 172-175)
    - Studio: Huntington, New York, Undated (Box 12, Folder 176)
    - Uniplate projector, 1952 (Box 12, Folder 177)
    - "The Vikings", 1928-1930 (Box 12, Folder 178-179)
    - Writings, 1923-1942 (Box 12, Folder 180-181)
  - Lumia
    - General information, 1918-1967 (Box 13, Folder 182-183)
    - Basic data, Undated (Box 13, Folder 184-185)
    - Clippings, Undated (Box 13, Folder 186)
      See also: box 1
    - Compositions
      - Numbers 136-160, Undated (Box 13, Folder 187-188)
      - Number 152, Undated (Box 13, Folder 189)
      - Number 155, Undated (Box 13, Folder 190)
      - Number 158, Undated (Box 14, Folder 191-192)
      - Number 162, Undated (Box 14, Folder 193)
      - Notes, 1952-1968 (Box 14, Folder 194-195)
    - Denmark, 1944-1945 (Box 14, Folder 196)
    - Direct Bearn Projector, 1953 (Box 14, Folder 197)
    - Drawings, Undated (Box 14, Folder 198)
      See also: boxes 22-23, folders 243-244
      See also: box 7-8, folders 116-117
    - Exhibitions, Circa 1955-1976 (Box 14, Folder 199)
    - Hall of Light, Undated (Box 14, Folder 200)
    - Heptarena Theatre, Undated (Box 14, Folder 201)
    - Ideas and plans, Undated (Box 15, Folder 202)
    - Lecture, Undated (Box 15, Folder 203)
    - Letters, Undated (Box 15, Folder 204-206)
    - Lute, Undated (Box 15, Folder 207)
    - Medal, Undated (Box 15, Folder 208)
    - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 15, Folder 209)
    - Multiplate scenic projector, Undated (Box 15, Folder 210)
    - Museum of Fine Art, New York, 1904-1965 (Box 15, Folder 211)
    - Odd instruments, Undated (Box 15, Folder 212)
    - Programs, Circa 1924-1925 (Box 15, Folder 213)
    - Projected scenery
      - Hotel Sherman, Chicago, Illinois, 1956 (Box 16, Folder 214-215)
      - Instruments and settings, Undated (Box 16, Folder 216)
    - Sidenius, W. Christian
      See also: box 4, folder 61
      - Clippings, Circa 1960-1969 (Box 15, Folder 217)
      - Lumia theatre, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 218)
    - Stein, Donna: thesis on lumia, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 219)
    - Studios, recital instruments, compositions, Undated (Box 16, Folder 220)
    - Summer course, 1942 (Box 16, Folder 221)
    - Surveys and miscellanea, 1938-1940 (Box 16, Folder 222)
    - Television, 1939-1949 (Box 16, Folder 223)
    - Writings and drawings, Undated (Box 17, Folder 224-226)
    - Writings by others, 1918-1980 (Box 18, Folder 227-228)
    - Writings by others, 1914-1939 (Box 19, Folder 229-233)
    - Writings by others, 1942-1975 and undated (Box 20, Folder 234-238)
  - Miscellanea regarding Thomas Wilfred
    - Lute, 1914-1918 (Box 26, Folder 253-255)
    - Obituaries, Circa 1968 (Box 26, Folder 256)
    - Photographs, portraits and others, Undated (Box 26, Folder 257-259)
- Additional material, Circa 1947-1993; Accession 1995-M-038; 0.38; (2 boxes)
  This accession comprises a typescript and a videotape relating to Wilfred's Lumia project.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access Restriction: Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  - Lumia, the Art of Light by Thomas Wilfred, annotated typescript, Circa 1947-1950 (Box 1)
  - A History of Lumia, 1993 September 14; Videotape (VHS). (Box 2)
    - Duplicating master, Videotape (VHS). (Box 2-D)
- Additional material, Circa 1940-1992; Accession 1996-M-029
  This accession comprises correspondence and printed materials of Bulat Galeyev; research notes; and visual and printed materials relating to Wilfred's Lumia project and other compositions.
  Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  This accession also includes Accession 2010-M-026, folders 19-23 in box 1.
  - Correspondence from Bulat Galeyev to W. Christian Sidenius, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence between John Ashby Conway and Thomas Wilfred re Clavilux, 1949 December-1963 February (Box 1, Folder 19-21)
  - Pamphlets and books
    - Thomas Wilfred: Lumia Suite, Opus 158 (New York: Museum of Modern Art), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Thomas Wilfred: Lumia: A Retrospective Exhibition, by Donna M. Stein, Corcoran Gallery of Art, Washington D.C., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Pamphlets on Bulat M. Galeyev, Circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 3)
      In English and Russian.
    - Books and pamphlets in Russian, 1976-1992; 6 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Index cards relating to compositions, Circa 1940-1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Visual materials
    - Slides, Circa 1940s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
      Includes Lumia compositions, color-related research, John Healy work, and projected theater scenery.
    - Glass slides and negatives, Circa 1940s (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
      Includes lantern slides for Star I and II, and glass slides and negatives for theater projection scenery and various compositions and projects.
    - Glass negatives of various compositions and projects, Circa 1940s (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - Prints and film negatives, Circa 1940s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 10-18)
      Includes 20 W. 22nd Street and Grand Central Palace projection room (480 Lexington Avenue), New York City; Model G and early home-recorded compositions; 2100 watt, 60 volt direct-beam projector for scenery; Seamus unit; Opus 162 Lucata; and various compositions and projects.
    - Photograph of Thomas Wilfred, Circa 1971 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Lumia sampler and "Lightscape", 1983; Videotape (VHS) (Box 2)
    - Duplicating master, Videotape (VHS) (Box 2-D)
- Additional material, Circa 1959-1961; Accession 1997-M-012
  This accession comprises correspondence between Wilfred and Raymond Epstein regarding the purchase of a composition.
  - Correspondence, Circa 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)